A Guide to the Papers of Professor K. Edward Lay ca. 1967-1993, and 1997-1999
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Professor K. Edward Lay ca. 1967-1993, and 1997-1999
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12817
This collection consists of ca. 4,300 items (7 Hollinger boxes, 3 linear feet). 1 arbitrary_unit
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These papers were given to the University of Virginia Library by K. Edward Lay, School of Architecture, Campbell Hall, University of Virginia, and transferred through Jack Robertson, Fiske-Kimball Fine Arts Library, on July 2, 1999.
Scope and Content Information
The papers of K. Edward Lay, Cary D. Langhorne Professor of Architecture, University of Virginia, ca. 1967-1993, and 1997-1999, ca. 4,300 items (7 Hollinger boxes) consist chiefly of slides and negatives of graduate and undergraduate student projects for the architectural design and architectural community involvement courses taught by Professor Lay. Included in the collection, are spiral bound notebooks containing photographs, drawings and news clippings for various student projects.
Also present are typescripts concerning the School of Architecture Administration & History, both compiled by K. Edward Lay, and a copy of a letter from Edwin A. Alderman to W.H. Pearson, August 1, 1908.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in two major groups of papers, the numbered spiral bound notebooks containing material concerning various University of Virginia architecture student projects (Boxes 1-3) and slides of University of Virginia architecture student projects (Boxes 3-7).
Contents List
- Spiral Bound Notebooks
  - 1) Architectural Community Involvement (ARCI)1971 (Box 1)
    includes: Hope House, the Downtown Mall, Simpson House, Community Action Organization (CAO), Volunteer Community Service Office, Charlottesville Community Service Center,Cavalier Daily Special Issue, Camp Faith Posters
  - 2) Third Year Architectural Design1967-1968 (Box 1)
    includes: projects for Art Center Ecology; Fan Mountain Astronomical Complex; Tension Structures; and the Community Action Organization Hope House
  - 3) Third Year Architectural Design1968-1969 (Box 1)
    includes: projects for Camp Faith, Charlottesville-Albemarle County Area; an Observation Tower; and the Richmond/James River area
  - 4) Third Year Architectural Design1969-1970 (Box 1)
    includes: projects for Loft Mountain Visitors Center in Shenandoah National Park; Hotel, Restaurant, Shops at Grace Street Block, Richmond; and Medical Offices, Club, & Shops, Richmond
  - 5) Third Year Architectural Design1970-1971 (Box 2)
    includes: projects for Housing Site Plan; Belle Isle, Richmond; Research in Environment Systems; Elementary School; and Center for Research and Innovation in Buildings (CRIB) Research
  - 6) Architectural Design Graduate Level1971-1972 (Box 2)
    includes: projects for Richmond Waterfront Development High Rise; Georgetown Waterfront; and Third Year Architectural Design projects, including Bakery; Greenhouse; and Communal Living
  - 7) Architectural Design Classes in Architectural Community Involvement (ARCI)1971-1972 (Box 2)
    includes: projects for Camp Holiday Trails, Inc.; Renovation of Hope House Exterior; and Experimental Mall Day
  - 8) Architectural Design Classes1972-1973 (Box 2)
    includes: projects for the National Park Information Center; University of Virginia Faculty Residence; Crafts Center; Urban Waterfront Design; Peyton Hall; Monticello Visitors Center Competition; Texaco Service Station Competition; Norfolk Waterfront Development Competition; and Studies in Vernacular Architecture
  - 9) Architectural Design Classes1973-1975 (Box 3)
    includes: projects for the Bicentennial Visitors Center; Prototype Building System; Transportation Redevelopment; National Design Competition in Corrections Architecture; Corrections Architecture; a Pub; Brown Street Housing; Courts Complex; Marina; Torpedo Plant; Macchu Picchu Competition (A Hotel and Study Facility at an Archaeological Site)
  - 10) Measured Drawings Studies in Vernacular Architecture, including news clippings concerning the class1973-1975 (Box 3)
  - Typescripts concerning the School of Architecture Administration & History1997-1999 (Box 3)
    both compiled by K. Edward Lay, and a copy of a letter from Edwin A. Alderman to W.H. Pearson, August 1, 1908
  - Studio Project Negatives Notebook - Projects listed in front of notebook1980-1993 (Box 3)
- Slides of University of Virginia Student Projects
  - Slides of UVA Architecture Student Projects (Arch. 23, 31, & 32)1967-1971 (Box 3)
    includes an ecology project; color project; Richmond hotel, theater, housing and shops; Shenandoah Park Visitor's Center; Belle Isle; an Elementary School, and Hope House (ACRI)
  - Slides of UVA Architecture Student Projects (Arch. 32)1972 Spring (Box 4)
    includes: a Bakery; Communal Living; and a Greenhouse
  - Slides of UVA Architecture Student Projects1972 Spring (Box 4)
    includes: Architecture Community Involvement Health Camp and Georgetown Thesis
  - Slides of UVA Architecture Student Projects (Arch. 31 & 101)1972 Fall (Box 4)
    includes: Information Center; Crafts Center; a House; and Georgetown Townhouses, Old Market, Landscaping, and Restaurant
  - Slides of UVA Architecture Student Projects (Arch. 41 & 42)1973 (Box 4)
    includes: Monticello Center; Norfolk Project; Service Station; Charlottesville Transportation Center; Bicentennial Center; and Prototype Restaurant & Bank
  - Slides of UVA Architecture Student Projects (Arch. 301 & 802)1974 (Box 4)
    includes: Pub; Brown Street Housing; National Competition Citations & Prizes; and Ice Rink
  - Slides of UVA Architecture Student Projects (Arch. 402)1975 (Box 4)
    includes: Alexandria Torpedo Plant, Marina, Athletic Club, and Court Offices; and Macchu Picchu Competition
  - Slides of UVA Architecture Student Projects (Arch. 301,503, & 701)1975-1976 (Box 5)
    includes: Crafts Center; Hotel on Shockoe Slip, Richmond; Theaters; Analysis; and Birdwood Residential College
  - Slides of UVA Architecture Student Projects (Arch. 402)1977 (Box 5)
    includes: Fredericksburg Urban Design, City Hall, Waterfront, Athletic Center, Arts & Crafts Center, Inn, and Entertainment Center
  - Slides of UVA Architecture Student Projects (Arch. 302)1979 (Box 5)
    includes: Railroad Depot; West Main Street Urban Study; and Y.M.C.A. Fredericksburg
  - Slides of UVA Architecture Student Projects (Arch. 302)1980 (Box 5)
    includes: a High School and Mt. Vernon Visitor's Center
  - Slides of UVA Architecture Student Projects (Arch. 301)1981 Fall (Box 5)
    includes: A Luxury Hotel and the Richmond Visitor's Center
  - Slides of UVA Architecture Student Projects (Arch. 302)1981 Spring (Box 5)
    includes: A Visual Arts Center and Restaurant
  - Slides of UVA Architecture Student Projects (Arch. 302 & 401)1982-1983 (Box 5)
    includes: A Restaurant; and a Washington, D.C. Orientation Center, Hotel, and an Embassy
  - Slides of UVA Architecture Student Projects (Arch. 401)1983 (Box 6)
    includes: A Facade Study and Charlottesville Transportation Center; and the AIA Virginia Society Prize Competition
  - Slides of UVA Architecture Student Projects (Arch. 301 & 402)1984 (Box 6)
    includes: Athletic Center; Architecture Association; Alexandria Waterfront; and Phoenix Charrette
  - Slides of UVA Architecture Student Projects (Arch. 301 & 401)1985-1986 (Box 6)
    includes: Botanical Garden; Visitor's Center; Library; and Visitor's Center; Columbus, Indiana
  - Slides of UVA Architecture Student Projects (Arch. 301 & 402)1987 (Box 6)
    includes: University of Virginia Architecture School; Color Facade; Presidential Museum; and Night Club
  - Slides of UVA Architecture Student Projects (Arch. 402)1988 (Box 6)
    includes: Embassies in Washington, D.C.
  - Slides of UVA Architecture Student Projects (Arch. 301, 402)1989 (Box 7)
    includes: A Presidential Library, Princeton University; Library; and Night Club
  - Slides of UVA Architecture Student Projects (Arch. 301)1990 (Box 7)
    includes: Housing and Three Generation Housing
  - Slides of UVA Architecture Student Projects (Arch. 302)1991 Spring (Box 7)
    includes: Museum V.C. and Fire Station
  - Slides of UVA Architecture Student Projects (Arch. 301)1991 Fall (Box 7)
    includes: Housing and A Grand House
  - Slides of UVA Architecture Student Projects (Arch. 301)1992 Fall (Box 7)
    includes: Jackson Park Housing and "S-Ville" House